Guide to the Office of the Chancellor: Barnes Woodhall Records, 1969-1971 UA.06.50.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of the Chancellor: Barnes Woodhall Records
1969-1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Woodhall, Barnes
UA.06.50.0001
5.5 Linear Feet
Contains correspondence, addresses, reports, memoranda, clippings and printed material documenting Woodhall's role in the governance of the University. Topics include the student unrest of the period, such as the Allen Building takeover and Vietnam War protests, unionization of the Medical Center, the management of University-owned housing, as well as Duke Forest.
Access Restrictions
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Provenance
Transfer,
Historical Note
Barnes Woodhall served as the Special Assistant to the President and then Chancellor pro tem from 1969-1970. Born January 22, 1905 in Rockport, ME, he was educated at Williams College (A.B., 1926) and Johns Hopkins University (M.D., 1930) and became a neurosurgeon. He held several positions at Duke University including appointments as Dean of the School of Medicine and Vice Provost of Medical Affairs. He died in 1985.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, addresses, reports, memoranda, clippings and printed material documenting Woodhall's role in the governance of the University. Topics include the student unrest of the period, such as the Allen Building takeover and Vietnam War protests, unionization of the Medical Center, the management of University-owned housing, as well as Duke Forest.
Much of the collection is made up of folders Woodhall labeled memorabilia, grouped by month, which include correspondence, copies of newsclippings, Office of Information Services releases, invitations, programs, and other materials. For each month, Woodhall wrote a brief summary of the events and activities that occurred, which sometimes includes commentary or reflection, usually succinct. Most of these events and activities are represented to some degree in the folder.
1969 folders include materials about student protests, including the Allen Building Takeover, and administrative activities around Woodhall's appointmentment as the first Chancellor in the wake of President Knight's announcement of retirement. These folders also include a large number of newsclippings from around the county related to student protests, student involvement in academia, and administrative activities at Duke and elsewhere. 1969 and 1970 folders include some materials about the retirement of Douglas Knight and the selection of Terry Sanford as President of Duke University. Materials from June 1970 on focus primarily on activities in the Medical Center, including the founding of the Davison Club, and Woodhall's professional activities as a neurosurgeon, including his attendance of the Congress of Neurological Surgeons in October 1970 and naming as a Statesman of Medicine in 1971.
The bulk of the memorabilia is made up of news releases and newsclippings. Much of the original material is related to the Medical Center. A smaller portion is related to Woodhall's activities as the Special Assistant to the President and then as Chancellor Pro Tem of the University. These materials include correspondence with administrators and members of the Board of Trustees as well as letters from friends, faculty, and members of the public, and other materials.
The remainder of the collection is made up of subject files, alphabetical by topic, which also includes some correspondence, printed matter, and other materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Conditions Governing Access
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Student protest; Student-administrator relationships; Labor unions -- Organizing; Neurosurgeons -- Societies, etc.; Duke University. Medical Center -- History; Knight, Douglas M., 1921-2005; Sanford, Terry
- Memorabilia, 1969 January; 2 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia, 1969 February; 2 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia, 1969 March; 3 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia, 1969 April; 2 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia, 1969 May; 2 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia, 1969 June; 2 (Box 2)
- Memorabilia, 1969 July; 1 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia, 1969 August; 1 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia, 1969 September; 2 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia, 1969 October; 3 (Box 3)
- Memorabilia, 1969 November; 2 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia, 1969 December; 2 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia, Misc., 1969; 2 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia, 1970 January; 2 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia, 1970 February; 2 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia, 1970 March; 2 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia, 1970 April; 2 (Box 6)
- Memorabilia, 1970 May; 2 (Box 6)
- Memorabilia, 1970 June; 2 (Box 6)
- Memorabilia, 1970 July; 1 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1970 August; 1 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1970 September; 1 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1970 October; 3 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1970 November; 1 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1970 December; 1 (Box 7)
- Memorabilia, 1971 January; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 February; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 March; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 April; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 May; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 June; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 July; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 August; 1 (Box 8)
- Memorabilia, 1971 September; 3 (Box 9)
- Memorabilia, 1971 October; 2 (Box 9)
- Memorabilia, 1971 December; 1 (Box 9)
- ACT, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Addresses and Reports, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Advancement Calendar, 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- Afro-American Corridor, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- American Civil Liberties Union, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- ACT Library, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Association of American Universities, 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- AAU Council on Federal Relations, 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- Atomic Energy Commission (Award to Dr. Gross), 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Buildings, Dedicated Of, 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- Buildings, Naming Of, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Budd Committee (Comm. On Afro-American Studies), 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Campus Club, 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- Carnegie Corp. (Physicians' Ass'ts. Program), 1969-1970; 1 (Box 10)
- Community Relations, 1969-1971; 1 (Box 10)
- Convocation, 1969; 1 (Box 10)
- Demonstrations-Allen Bldg. (Letters from and Resources' to Alumni), 1969 (Box 11)
- Enrollment, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
- Equal Opportunity Employment, 1970 (Box 11)
- Fiber Industries, Inc. (Duke Forest), 1969 (Box 11)
- Fifth Decade, 1969 (Box 11)
- Founders' Day, 1970 (Box 11)
- Johnson, Steve, Assistant to the Chancelor, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
- Harry R. Jackson - Alumni Publications (Allen Bldg. Take-Over), 1969-1970 (Box 11)
- Major Gifts - Institutional Advancement, 1969 (Box 11)
- MOBE (Mobilization to End the Vietnam War), 1969 (Box 11)
- Students - Organization, 1969 (Box 11)
- Students - Privacy, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
- Student - Records, 1967-1969 (Box 11)
- Students - Regulations, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
- Student Representation, 1969 (Box 11)
- Trustee Meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
- Tuition, 1964-1969 (Box 11)
- University House, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
- Wachoria Bank, 1963-1970 (Box 11)
- William M. Werber (Allen Bldg. Take-Over), 1969 (Box 11)
- Winchester Excarations, 1970 (Box 11)
- Memorabilia: Restricted, 1969 January (Box 11)
- Memorabilia: Restricted, Oct 1969 (Box 11)
- Memorabilia: Restricted, Jan 1970 (Box 11)
- Memorabilia: Board of Trustees, 1970 (Box 11)
- Trustee Meetings, 1970 (Box 11)